It's really great to see you made it all the way through this challenging lesson.
很高兴 你已经完成了这节高难度课
In the project description, you will find everything you need to know to
在实战项目描述里 你会找到关于成功完成项目
successfully complete the project.
所需的所有资源
In this video,
在本视频中
I would like to point out some things about the UKF I find quite remarkable.
我想指出 UKF 一些非常了不起的地方
And I also want to explain why a Kalman filter in general
此外 我还想解释一下 为什么
is such an important tool for self driving cars.
卡尔曼滤波器对无人驾驶车而言 是如此重要
Let's have a look at the scenario in the project.
我们看看项目的这个场景
You have seen a similar plot before in the EKF project.
你之前在 EKF 项目里见过类似的图
We see here a bicycle that is first driving straight and
这里显示的是一辆自行车 首先直线行驶
then turning into a circle.
然后沿圆形转弯
The path of the bicycle is shown in blue.
自行车的路径用蓝色表示
The green line is the sequence of all measurements we receive both from LiDAR
绿线是我们从激光雷达和雷达收到
and radar.
的所有测量值序列
As before, these measurements are quite noisy.
和之前一样 这些测量值充满噪音
The orange dots are the estimation results of the UKF fusing laser and
橙色的点是 UKF 的估算来源 融合了激光
radar measurements.
和雷达测量值
Remember, the linear process model in the last project
记住 上一个实战项目里的线性过程模型
had problems following the turn.
在追踪拐弯时碰到了问题
The CTRV model we're using this time follows the turn quite nicely, and
我们这次使用的 CTRV 模型能很好地追踪拐弯
still provides a smooth position estimate.
并且提供平滑的位置估算
You can play around with the process noise values, and
你可以调整过程噪音值
make the estimation even smoother.
让评估更加平滑
Or force it to follow the measurements quicker.
或者强迫噪音更快地跟上测量值
When you change the process noise values,
改变过程噪音值时
also make sure to check the consistency of your filter.
还一定要检查滤波器的一致性
This is how the consistency check of my filter looks like.
我的滤波器一致性检查看起来是这样的
What you see here in orange are the NIS values of the three dimensional radar
这里的橙色是三维雷达测量值的
measurements.
NIS 值
I also plotted the 95% line in blue.
我还用蓝色画出了 95% 线
Just as expected, a small number if NIS values exceed this line.
和预期的一样 少量的 NIS 值超过了这条线
If your NIS values look like this,
如果你的 NIS 值是这样的
you know you have set up a consistent filter.
那么滤波器就是一致的
This is how the NIS values of the laser measurements look like.
这是激光测量值的 NIS 值的样子
Be aware that the 95% line is at a different level in this case
注意 这里的 95% 线位置不一样
because the laser measurement is a two dimensional vector.
因为激光测量值是一个二维向量
The project description will give you details about the exact criteria for
实战项目描述提供了成功进行
a successful consistency check.
一致性检查所需的准确标准详情
Remember if the UKF is consistent,
记住 如果 UKF 是一致的
it means it provides a realistic covariance matrix.
它就能够提供现实的协方差矩阵
The UKF also estimates the velocity of the bicycle of course.
当然 UKF 还能估算自行车的速度
It can do it with or without radar.
有没有雷达都可以
But if you compare these two options, you will find out
但是 如果你比较这两个选项
that the velocity estimate converges much faster if you use the radar too.
你会发现 如果使用了雷达 速度估算的收敛速度更快
Give it a try and switch on and off both sensors, and
你可以试试 打开并关闭两个传感器
see how they contribute in different ways.
看看它们各自有什么作用
What I find really impressive is how precise the UKF can estimate
让我印象深刻的是 UKF 评估自行车方向
the orientation of the bicycle.
非常精确
None of our sensors is able to directly observe the orientation, but
我们的传感器都无法直接观察方向
we still get a precise estimate.
但我们仍然得到了精确的估算
Even the yaw rate can be estimated providing useful results.
甚至角速度都能估算出来 提供了有用的结果
For autonomous vehicles,
对于无人驾驶车
the yaw rate of other vehicles is very important to know.
其他车辆的角速度很重要
Imagine another car starting to change lanes or
想像一下 另一辆车
a bicycle in front of you wants to do a left turn.
开始变道 或你前面的自行车想要左拐
Hopefully, they would both signalize their intention but in the end
当然 他们很可能都会发出信号
the yaw rate is the ultimate indicator for such a behavior prediction.
但角速度是最终的行为预测指标
Let's summarize the three most important properties of the UKF as
我们总结一下 UKF 作为无人驾驶的传感器融合工具
a sensor fusion tool for self driving cars.
有三个最重要的功能
Number one, with the UKF, you will be able to take noisy measurement data as input and
第一 在 UKF 中 你可以输入噪音测量数据
provide a smooth position and
并获得周围动态对象的
velocity estimation of dynamic objects around you, without introducing a delay.
位置和速度的平滑估算 不会引发延时
Number two, you can provide an estimation of the orientation and
第二 即便使用的传感器无法直接观察 你还是可以
the yaw rate of other vehicles using sensors that can't even directly observe
获得其他车辆的方向和角速度的
these things.
估算
And number three, in addition to that,
第三 除此以外
the UKF also gives information on how precise the result is,
UKF 还能给出结果的准确度
because it always provides a covariance matrix for every estimation.
因为它能提供每个故uande协方差矩阵
And you know that this covariance matrix is realistic if the UKF performs
如果 UKF 已经执行了一致性检查 你就能知道
a consistency check.
协方差矩阵是现实的
The uncertainty of the estimation result is very important for self driving cars.
估算结果的不确定性对无人驾驶车非常重要
Because if the position of your leading vehicle is quite uncertain at some time,
因为 如果在某个时刻 前方车辆的位置非常不确定
you better keep a little more distance
你最好多拉开点车距